<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Quakers looking-glass look'd upon; and turned toward himself; in a sober reply to an uncivll [sic] pamplet published by Luke Howard a Quaker, against a narrative formerly published, setting forth the folly and presumption of Charles Baily a Quaker, sometimes a prisoner in Dover ...</title>
            <author>Hobbs, Richard, 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86418</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2271</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R178062</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45789342</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45789342</idno>
            <idno type="VID">172652</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86418)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 172652)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2643:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Quakers looking-glass look'd upon; and turned toward himself; in a sober reply to an uncivll [sic] pamplet published by Luke Howard a Quaker, against a narrative formerly published, setting forth the folly and presumption of Charles Baily a Quaker, sometimes a prisoner in Dover ...</title>
                  <author>Hobbs, Richard, 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>13 [i.e. 15] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Francis Smith at the Elephant and Castle ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed: Richard Hobbs.</note>
                  <note>Numerous errors in paging.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Friends' Library (London, England).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Howard, Luke, 1621-1699. --  Looking-glass for Baptists.</term>
               <term>Bayley, Charles, 17th cent.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  England --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:172652:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE QUAKERS Looking-Glaſs Look'd upon; And turned towards Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; IN A SOBER REPLY TO AN Uncivll Pamplet Publiſhed by <hi>Luke Howard</hi> a Quaker, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt A NARRATIVE formerly Publiſhed, Setting forth the Folly and Preſumption of <hi>Charles Baily</hi> a Quaker, ſometimes a Priſoner in <hi>Dover.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which REPLY The Truth of the ſaid Narrative is further Evidenced and Vindicated againſt the Cavilling <hi>Quakers.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>There are many Devices in a Mans heart; Nevertheleſs, the Councel of the Lord ſhall ſtand,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 19.21.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>To the Law and to the Teſtimonies; If they ſpeak not according to this Word, It is becauſe there is no light in them,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſa. 8.20.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ONDON, Printed for <hi>Francis Smith</hi> at the <hi>Elephant</hi> and <hi>Caſtle,</hi> near the <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> in <hi>Cornhil.</hi> And alſo at the ſame Sign the firſt Shop without <hi>Temple-Barre.</hi> 1673.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:172652:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>FRiendly Reader,</hi> I do here Preſent thee with a ſmall Tract, Containing a Brief Reply to a Book put forth lately by <hi>Luke Howard</hi> a Quaker, Entituled, <hi>A Looking-Glaſs for the Baptiſts;</hi> The Contents of which Book, and the Intents of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor is to obſcure the Truth of the Narrative which is hereunto an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed, which Narrative is a Relation of ſome Remarkable Paſſages Concerning one <hi>Charles Baily</hi> an Eminent Quaker, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times a Priſoner in <hi>Dover</hi> upon the Quaking account, during which time of his ſaid Impriſonment thoſe (Extravigancies were commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by him) and alſo to reproach and defame the Publiſher of the ſaid Narrative; But how little he hath accompliſh'd his End in the firſt, (in oppoſing himſelf againſt ſo manifeſt a Truth) and how much he hath diſcovered his folly and envy in the latter, doth in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure appear in this following Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>I alſo hereby further certifie thee, That the aforeſaid Narrative was not Publiſhed to blemiſh the Perſons of the Quakers, nor yet from a ſpirit of Envie, as the Quaker would inſinuate, but to ſhew what enormities the pretended light (to which they make the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures give way and bow) leads them; And that thoſe that are in danger of being beguiled, by heeding a Light within themſelves, above the light of the Holy Scriptures, may not be deceived by them, to follow the uncertain motions of their own Heads, but may rather follow the Councel of the Apoſtle, <hi>2 Pet. 19.20 We have a more ſure word of the Prophets,</hi> (ſaith he) meaning the Scriptures, <hi>to which ye do well that ye take heed</hi> (mark) <hi>as unto a light that ſhineth in a dark Place,</hi> &amp;c. And finally, he that knows the hearts, knows that this is my end in Publiſhing both the Narrative and this, and he will one day decide all Controverſies depending between them and us, and then ſhall every man receive according to his Works; In the mean time read and conſider what follow: And ſo I leave thee to the Guidance and Bleſſing of the Lord,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>And remain, Thine in the Hope of Eternal Life by Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> Richard Hobbs.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:172652:2"/>
            <p>THIS Quakers <hi>Looking-Glaſſe</hi> is falſe, it preſents two Faces, one as if they did, another as if they did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Charles Baily</hi> for an eminent Quaker; And that this is ſo, ſee what he ſaith <hi>page</hi> 10. <hi>viz.</hi> ſome new Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted Friends, ſaith he, did own <hi>Charles Baily;</hi> but the Men Friends, (meaning himſelf and three or four more Priſoners in the Caſtle) did not own him ſo much; But this we did not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint the Baptiſts with, ſaith he; Hence note, <hi>Luke Howard</hi> appears in his <hi>Looking-Glaſs</hi> with two Faces; Firſt, one toward the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> as if he did own <hi>Charles Baily</hi> as an eminent <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker,</hi> but now as with another Face he pretends it was not ſo much as we did think; And here his Glaſs is true if turned towards him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but falſe to the <hi>Baptiſts,</hi> becauſe we know not (as himſelf confeſſeth,) but that he owned <hi>Baily</hi> as much as the reſt did. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, from hence we may alſo note by the way, what little Cauſe the Man hath to make ſuch an Out-cry againſt the Baptiſts, as if they forged and publiſhed falſhoods, when we ſay no more then himſelf confeſſeth, That to our knowledge they did own <hi>Baily</hi> a that time for an eminent <hi>Quaker.</hi> The which <hi>I</hi> ſhall make fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther appear by theſe three following Particulars.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. That the ſaid <hi>Baily</hi> did prophecie, ſee falſe Viſions, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to work Miracles, as appears by the Narrative hereunto an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed.</item>
               <item>2. That he was then in fellowſhip with the <hi>Quakers,</hi> and owned by them.</item>
               <item>3. That <hi>Baily</hi> was led by the <hi>Quakers</hi> ſpirit into theſe delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</item>
               <item>4. Examine the <hi>Quakers</hi> evaſions, by which he endeavors to ſhift off the Truth of our Narrative.</item>
               <item>5. Pluck up by the roots the Authors prodigious root of the <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> and diſcover the Authors Apoſtacy from the Truth.</item>
               <item>6. By ſome ſober reflexions upon his falſe accuſations, as they are ſcattered through his book.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt, that the <hi>Quakers</hi> did own <hi>Baily</hi> for an eminent <hi>Quaker</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them before and after his pretended Viſion, Prophecie and Miracles mentioned in the Narrative, appears, by their then af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming and juſtifying him to be led by the true Light, as they did by their hearing him preach, and devoutly joyning with him in Prayer.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:172652:3"/>
            <p>But this is a poor Proof, ſaith our <hi>Looking-Glaſs-Maker,</hi> pag. 9. To which anſwer, That if this be not a ſufficient proof they owned him. <hi>I</hi> know not what is or can be ſufficient, nor do <hi>I</hi> know any Rule the <hi>Quakers</hi> have, by which <hi>I</hi> ſhall know when they own one another. But to ſhift this off, the <hi>Quaker</hi> ſays, they were only new convinced friends that owned <hi>Baily;</hi> Himſelf and three or four more then in priſon with him, did not own him ſo much. <hi>Reply.</hi> If by (ſo much) you mean ye did not joyn with him in his devotion, <hi>I</hi> grant it; for your reſtraint from him hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered you in that; but at the ſame time ye juſtified him as highly as the reſt in your Diſcourſe concerning him and his actions, and condemned the <hi>Baptiſts</hi> for oppoſing him in his fooliſh attempts, though now ye would have the World believe, ye did not own him ſo much as friends at liberty did.</p>
            <p>As if all the <hi>Quakers</hi> in <hi>Dover</hi> and <hi>Folkſtone,</hi> and thereabouts, that had fellowſhip with <hi>Baily,</hi> and were daily privy to his words and actions, were ſo Moon-blind, that they could not ſee <hi>Baily</hi> was led by a falſe light, ſo well as our Looking-Glaſs-Maker could, through the ſtone-walls of <hi>Dover</hi>-Caſtle, ſee how this man lifts up himſelf above his brethren.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Luke,</hi> to heal up this tells us, That friends abroad were afraid to judge <hi>Baily,</hi> but when they came to the <hi>Quakers</hi> in the Caſtle, they would ſpeak the thing as it was, and that <hi>Baily</hi> erred.</p>
            <p>But this we did not think fit to acquaint the <hi>Baptiſts</hi> with, ſaith he. <hi>Reply.</hi> Behold, here is the <hi>Quakers</hi> Method: That al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they know a thing to be true and juſtly charged upon them, yet it is their prudence to deny or not acknowledge it, That they may preſerve the reputation of their erroneous light; and thoſe poor ſilly ſouls that are led aſide thereby, and contrary to their knowledge and conſcience will juſtifie the evil doer, and bear world in hand as if the Baptiſts were tranſgreſſors for ſpeaking the thing that is true.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That <hi>Baily</hi> was owned by the quakers as one in fellowſhip with them, and that not only by new converted friends without, but alſo by <hi>Luke</hi> and his Brethren within the Caſtle, is further mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, that after his fooliſh prophecy, viſion and miracles they did Juſtifie him in thoſe his fopperies before <hi>Suſanna Tavenor,</hi> and condemnd her as a lying envious perſon becauſe ſhe ſaid to <hi>Luke</hi> and the reſt in Priſon, that <hi>Baily</hi> had propheſied falſly in the name
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:172652:3"/>of the Lord, and had ſeen a falſe Viſion, (meaning that mentioned in the Narrative, and ſo violent they were againſt her for ſo ſaying, that ſhe could not be at quiet amongſt them when ſhe came to the priſon to viſit her then husband <hi>John VVarriſon,</hi> who was a <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker,</hi> and then in priſon with <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke,</hi> and the other <hi>Quakers</hi> in the Caſtle; Again, that they did own him for an eminent <hi>Quaker</hi> is further evident, in that divers of them went to him for cure of their divers diſeaſes; As for inſtance, <hi>Luke Howard</hi> (our Looking-Glaſs-Maker) and <hi>An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e</hi> his then Wife, went to him to be cuted of her ſore eyes; and <hi>Baily</hi> touch'd them, (as his manner was, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to cure her, and ſhe reported that he had cured her; and this <hi>Luke</hi> knows in his own Conſcience is true.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe <hi>Katherine Fernn</hi> a quaker now living in <hi>Dover</hi> came to him to be cured of Convulſion fits, and reported that ſhe had received cure by him, alſo <hi>Edward Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>isbee</hi> of <hi>Deal</hi> another Quaker to be cured of his ſore legg, which he ſaid he alſo received cure for. by <hi>Baily,</hi> and thereupon he threw away all his plaiſters, and clouts that formerly he uſed. And this was trumpeted about town and Country, that <hi>Charles Baily</hi> a quaker being then in <hi>Dover</hi> Priſon had an extraordinary gift healing, by which (as they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported) he had cured Divers, inſomuch that divers others that were not Quakers came to the priſon to him for cure, namely <hi>William Williams,</hi> who had a ſwelling in his face, and <hi>Baily</hi> ſtroakt it in order to cure, and <hi>Samuel Tavenor</hi> came from <hi>Dcale</hi> (upon <hi>Edward Salisbee</hi>'s report of theſe cures, to adviſe with <hi>Baily</hi> about the cure of his Wife who had bin long weak and lame. But of all theſe he cured not one except the Quakers, nor all them neither, as ſome of the Quakers have in my hearing lately confeſſed; yet had he Caſt the Devil out of <hi>Woollet</hi> but as effectually as the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers ſay he cured them, (which he ſaid had been done if ſome of the Baptiſts had not been preſent) doubtleſs he had been cryed up for that miracle far more then for all the reſt of his fooliſh projects but now the poor man failing in their loſſes the honour of all the reſt, ſo that to conclude this particular, I ſay, if the Quakers com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>Baily</hi> to be taught by him, to be healed by him, to pray with him and to Juſtifie his words and actions againſt all oppoſers, and to give him the hand and fixt look, were owning of him, then did our looking-glaſs-maker himſelf and his Bretheren in this Town and hereabouts own <hi>Baily</hi> as a moſt eminent Quaker, both at and after the projects he playd mentioned in the Narrative.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That <hi>Baily</hi> was led by the Quakers ſpirit, <hi>Luke</hi> will by no
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:172652:4"/>means allow, and ſo acquit himſelf from the crime of being led by a deluding ſpirit, he ſayes <hi>Baily</hi> was not guided by their ſpirit, when he acted as in the Narrative is expreſſed, in page the twelfth, of his Looking-glaſs he ſaith, This Baptiſt Paſtor and many of his flock and of his mind would have the world believe that <hi>Charles Baily</hi> and the reſt of the Quakers were led by one and the ſame ſpirit when he erred in his heart.</p>
            <p>To this <hi>I</hi> reply, and ſay, he was led by the Quakers ſpirit &amp; preached their doctrine, and was in all reſpects as deep died a Quaker as <hi>Luke Howard</hi> himſelf, and if <hi>Luke</hi> had uſed a little more plainneſs, and told us when and in what <hi>Baily</hi> Erred, he had ſaved me ſome labour to Query when he ſo erred, if <hi>Luke</hi> mean in the Buſineſs of <hi>Woollet;</hi> I graunt he did err in that, but he did not in that err from the Quakers, for it is evident he was moved by the dictates of the ſame ſpirit, by which he pretended to cure the Quakers, in which they highly owned him, and doubtleſs his and their deſign in thoſe attempts of his, was to confirm their doctrine and to proſelite the Baptiſts to the owning of their principles, and to this purpoſe he called the Baptiſts to ſee this Tragedie, and told them they ſhould ſee the Power of God. And that he might further ſhew this to be his intent, he deſired God to ſhew his Power for the confirmation of his Eternal truth, as he did of old Againe, that he was Carried forth into that action by the Quakers ſpirit: Appears by the opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and working of it with him at that time; which was in the ſame kind and after the ſame manner that it frequently had done in other Quakers, viz. By its violent motions, throwing him down upon the floore, as it alſo handled another Quaker about the ſame time in the ſame Priſon, where he lay ſome time upon the floore, Plunging and Beating himſelf, and Groaning as if he would have given up the Ghoſt (and this Perſon is now none of the meaneſt Quakers in <hi>Dover</hi>) nor did the poſture and actings of <hi>Bailys</hi> two female companions that joyned with him in that attempt upon <hi>Woollet,</hi> ſhew any other but that he and they were all led and acted by the ſame ſpirit; nay, and <hi>I</hi> my ſelf have ſeen the ſame ſpirit ſhew it ſelf by the ſame operation upon our Looking Glaſs-Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker himſelf, making him quake and ſhake, that people without doors heard the violent noiſe of it; by which it appears, that <hi>Baily</hi> and the reſt of the <hi>Quakers</hi> are led by one and the ſame ſpirit.</p>
            <p>And it is evident alſo <hi>Baily</hi> was acted by the ſame ſpirit with the Quakers, in his Viſion and Prophecie againſt me, and the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:172652:4"/>that he denounced againſt me; for that which gave the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion was, my oppoſing him and them in their <hi>Quaking</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples and Doctrine; and doubtleſs, he did as much deſign the Confirmation and Crediting their doctrine in this, as he did in the other of his Projects<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But if <hi>Luke</hi> think <hi>Baily</hi> erred in this his attempt concerning me, I think ſo too; and that our Look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-Glaſs-Maker and the reſt of the <hi>Quakers</hi> erred with him ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: for they juſtified him and condemned me as he did. Truly, if <hi>Luke</hi> had told us in what <hi>Baily</hi> erred, and for what they now deny him, as he pretends, his Glaſs had been clearer, and he had done his Cauſe ſome right, in taking off a juſt ground of ſuſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that <hi>Baily</hi> firſt forſook them ſeeing himſelf deluded by them.</p>
            <p>From all this it evidently appears, That neither the Paſtor nor any of his Flock (as <hi>Luke</hi> ſcoffingly words it) do wrong the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> at all, in ſaying that <hi>Baily</hi> was a <hi>Quaker,</hi> and led by their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit at the time of his Projects mentioned in their Narrative: But to wipe away all this, <hi>Luke</hi> tells us, that <hi>Baily</hi> is departed from them, and therefore they are not to be charged with his Actions, no more then the Chriſtians of old with thoſe that departed from them: and ſeems to be much offended, <hi>pag.</hi> 13. <q>What now, <hi>Baptiſt</hi>-Paſtor, (ſaith he) wouldeſt thou have judged all the diſciples, becauſe <hi>Peter</hi> denied his Maſter, and for <hi>Judas</hi>'s ſake, have ſaid they were all alike, and led by one and the ſame ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> And then, as if the Man thought himſelf an Artiſt at Looking-Glaſs-making, he ſays, <hi>See thy face thou blinde Paſtor, thy Jewiſh ſpirit would have accuſed all the Brethren for their ſakes, that went out from them, and have ſaid they were all alike, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> The caſe in hand between <hi>Luke</hi> and I is not equivolent, to that he alludes to, for neither <hi>Peter</hi> nor <hi>Judas</hi> did pretend, in denying their Maſter, to advance their Miniſtry and the Goſpel, as <hi>Charles Baily</hi> did the <hi>Quakers</hi> doctrine, in what he did in his Prophecie, Revelation and prodigious Miracles: And therefore it would have been as impertinent for any to have charged all the Apoſtles with their ſin, who never owned them in it, as the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> did <hi>Baily</hi> in what he did, as 'tis proper for me to ſay, That <hi>Baily</hi> was led by the <hi>Quakers</hi> ſpirit: And the caſe of them which went out of the Church, <hi>John</hi> 2.19. to which <hi>Luke Howard</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ludes, makes as little to his purpoſe, for they departed from the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles doctrine, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.43. (as <hi>Luke</hi> himſelf has done) and their caſe is more applicable to himſelf then to <hi>Charles Baily,</hi> who ſo
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:172652:5"/>highly owned the quakers doctrine at that time that he preached it up, ſuffered for it, Pronounced Judgment againſt the oppoſers of it; and pretended to work miracles to confirm it, and therefore, his being rather an act of perſevereing in, then a departing from your Spirit and doctrine, quite alters the Caſe and all <hi>Lukes</hi> Cavilling compariſons fall to the ground; But <hi>Luke</hi> goes further, and to Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure his reader that <hi>Baily</hi> was no ſober quaker when he acted as in the narrative expreſſed, he terms them mad Actions, page 8.</p>
            <p>Reply, <hi>Luke,</hi> in this is very uncharitable methinks to his old Friend, (though then he and the reſt of the Quakers befriended him) in that they Judge <hi>Baily</hi> now according to thr event of his actions, and not according to the intent of his mind, which was to advance that which <hi>Luke</hi> calls truth, and as diſingenious to himſelf, ſeeing he is led by the ſame ſpirit by which <hi>Baily</hi> then acted, nor is <hi>Luke</hi> leſs Injurous to his two female Friends, who were as madd in that madd action (about <hi>Woollet</hi>) as <hi>Baily</hi> was, but thoſe he wholly ſcreens from the world in his glaſs, and lett<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them not be ſeen therein at all, though he know in his conſcience they are co-workers with <hi>Baily</hi> in that undertaking, but this argues that <hi>Bailys</hi> leaving them ſince that time is his greateſt crime, and therefore the Burthen is by <hi>Luke</hi> laid and left upon <hi>Bailys</hi> back, and the two female friends are Befriended.</p>
            <p>But laſtly, <hi>Luke</hi> to cleer the caſe at once, tells his Reader in the ſame page, That they are as cleer from <hi>Charles Baily</hi> in the ſight of God, as they are from us: Reply, That <hi>Luke Howard</hi> is cleer from us <hi>I</hi> graunt. For he (long ſince) left the Baptiſts and turned a lewd Ranter, ſcoffing at, and oppoſing the ordinances of Chriſt then, at he doth now. But he was no more cleer from <hi>Baily</hi> when he acted as in the Narrative then <hi>Judah</hi> was from his ſin with <hi>Tha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar;</hi> when ſhe had his Bracelets, Signet and Staff, for then <hi>Baily</hi> had their ſpirit, held their principles, and Preached their Doctrine, and here is an end of his ſhifts to evade the truth or Narratve concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Baily</hi> and his fellow Females.</p>
            <p>In the next place, I ſhall (according to what <hi>I</hi> have propound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) take off his evaſions, by which he endeavours to darken the truth of the Narrative, and firſt, <hi>Luke</hi> tells us in page the 10. That his Wife did ſend a Letter to <hi>London</hi> about <hi>Baily:</hi> Reply, how in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>congruous is this to reaſon, That ſhe on whom <hi>Baily</hi> had newly wrought a miracle, ſhould write againſt him, and that then the reſt of the Quakers here ſhould not know it, to diſown him with her,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:172652:5"/>no, nor no body elſe knew of it unrill now, let the judicious reader Judge of this.</p>
            <p>Again in the ſame page he tells us, two friends came and teſtified againſt <hi>Baily,</hi> but did not diſown him, nor does he pretend ſo, for <hi>Baily</hi> preached amongſt them after he came out of Priſon, which was ſome Months after his falſe Viſion, &amp;c. But was this known to the Baptiſts (who ſay <hi>Baily</hi> was a deceiver) that two friends had teſtified againſt him; No ſaith <hi>Luke,</hi> this we did not acquaint the Baptiſts with, and why ſo, why faith <hi>Luke</hi> becauſe we knew they waited for miſchief. Reply.</p>
            <p>What ſilly fenceleſs ſhifts are theſe, to evade that which <hi>Luke</hi> knowes in his own conſcience to be true. As if the only way to cutt off occaſion of reproach from ſuch as wait for it, were to own and Juſtifie the offender, and to condemn and cenſure the innocent and offended; And in page the 7. The Quaker to evade that which Juſtly ſticks upon him, tells the world that <hi>Baily</hi> was not eſtabliſht amongſt them. Reply,</p>
            <p>This is ſtrange (if true) what, one that zealouſly owned and preached up the Light within, confirmed the ſame doctrine by miracles (if the reports of Quakers may be credited) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced Judgments againſt the oppoſers thereof, and indured im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment for their doctrines ſake, and yet not be an eſtabliſhed Quakers<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> If theſe be not the indelible Characters of an eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed Quaker, let them ſhew me what they are, and by what rule; (if they have any) I may know which are, and which are not Eſtabliſhed Quakers; mean time they muſt needs give us leave to let <hi>Baily</hi> paſs for one, having all the forenamed Characters upon him.</p>
            <p>But in the next place the man, (to make his Glaſs Cleer) hee gives it a Rubb, and that (as he thinks) to purpoſe two: And do ye not know (ſaith he) in your conſciences, that he, viz. <hi>Baily,</hi> hath been by us called Quakers denyed for many years. Reply,</p>
            <p>But not a word, where when or for what he was denyed, and ſo ye make this evaſion impertinent your ſelf; And though ye do diſown him now, that is nothing to us in the caſe in hand, wee ſay in the Narrative that <hi>Baily</hi> was then owned by you, when he plaied thoſe prepoſterous Pranks, and was then led by the ſame ſpirit with you, and I have made it appear to be true, and <hi>I</hi> further ſay, <hi>I</hi> do not know whether you have yet denyed him (as
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:172652:6"/>ye term it) for ſome of ye have of late reported that he has paſt through the town and no: took ſo much notice of his old friends as might be expected, and methinks this ſmells as if he were not quite diſlocated from you, or elſe that this ſtrangneſs of his towards you, ariſes from this, that he perceiving himſelf to be deluded by your Light, he keeps a loof from you as a company of poor deluded and miſtaken Creatures. Another while, (in page 7. you have the Quaker ſpeaking in favour of his old friend a little, and tells us, that we have belyed him in ſome things, as bad as he was, or as we would make him to be, but names, no particulars wherein we have wronged him, Reply.</p>
            <p>To this I ſay, there is two wayes of wronging a man in this caſe, one is when we declare more of him then is true, the other is when wee do not declare all that is true, in the firſt of theſe I have not failed; But in the latter <hi>I</hi> have, and when <hi>I</hi> know in which of theſe two our Looking-glaſs-maker means <hi>I</hi> have wronged his friend in, it may be <hi>I</hi> may make him an amends.</p>
            <p>But in the mean time <hi>I</hi> ſhall go on to examine his prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous root.</p>
            <p>And firſt here <hi>I</hi> take notice, that whileſt <hi>Luke Howard</hi> is alar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruming the world againſt us, as if we were the veryeſt miſcreants that ever lived, for Blabbing out a tale of truth, which he would have had been hid, he clamours thus (what a thing of ten years ſtanding) that is the great crime, ſee page 8. and page the II. And you ſhall ſee he himſelf runns into the ſame tranſgreſſion over ſhooes and Boots two, and Retrogrades 28 Years back, to rake for matter to reproach us. This man ſure inſtead of making us a <hi>Looking-Glaſſe,</hi> had need have made himſelf a Proſpective-glaſſe, but to his ſtory, <hi>page</hi> the 5. in the years 1643. and 1644. ſaith he, the <hi>Baptiſts,</hi> had their entrance into <hi>Kent</hi> and many were Dipped by <hi>William Kiffin</hi> into the belief of particular election, and amongſt others <hi>Luke Howard</hi> and <hi>Nicholas Woodman</hi> profeſſed repentance and faith and were dipped, as <hi>Luke</hi> in deriſion terms it, and then in page the 8. he tells his reader, this <hi>Nicholas Weodman</hi> proved an idle perſon, he took a wife who married him for his profeſſion-ſake, that he proved a lewd man, ſpent his wifes eſtate, abuſed her body and then leſt her and went and Preached Water Baptiſme &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Reply<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For <hi>Nicholas Woodman, I</hi> know not whether there were ſuch a man or no, but by <hi>Luke Howards</hi> and ſome others re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:172652:6"/>who ſay, he lived as orderly as <hi>Luke Howard,</hi> for they both proved prophane ſinners againſt the Light and grace they had received from God, <hi>VVoodman</hi> to Idleneſs and looſe living, and <hi>Luke Howard</hi> to a wanton and lewd Ranter. And may not ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the ſame rule, that <hi>Luke</hi> upbraides us with <hi>VVoodmans</hi> bad living, twitt us with <hi>Luke Howards</hi> too, who was Baptized with him and caſt his looſs life as dirt in our faces; And in particular his Railing book that he has writ againſt us, in which he expreſſeth more enmity then our common oppoſers uſually do, But ſeeing our Looking-glaſſe-maker had no other but his Apoſtate Brothers faults to blemiſh us with, he would have ſeemed a wiſer man, and have done himſelf a kindneſs, to have concealed them, for no wiſe man would have raked in that hole where he knew his own Infamy lay buried<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But this ſhews the height of his anger a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Baptiſts, that he will pluck out his own Bowels but that he will beſmear them. Truly in this buſineſs our Looking-glaſſe-maker has as much need of a Looking-glaſſe as his neighbour, meane time, let him ſee and know, that <hi>Woodmans</hi> Bad living, and <hi>Luke Howards</hi> wanton actions, and ertoneous principles, are alike diſowned by the Bapttſts, They being alike contrary to Chriſts Doctrine and the Baptiſts Practice.</p>
            <p>And that the man might manifeſt himſelf ſo farr degenerate from his Baptiſme and faith, as if he had forgotten that Jeſus Chriſt is the root, in his own example and command of beleevers Baptiſme <hi>Math.</hi> 3. and <hi>Math</hi> 28.18. he tells us page 8. that <hi>Nicholas Woodman</hi> was the riſe and root of the Baptiſts in <hi>Kent,</hi> But that this Paragraph is falſe, Appears preſently from his own Pen, for he tells us many were Baptized in <hi>Kent</hi> by <hi>William Kiffin</hi> before <hi>Nicholas Woodman</hi> preached or Baptized any, for <hi>William Kiffin</hi> he ſaith Baptized <hi>Woodman,</hi> ſo that if a man be the root of the Baptiſts in <hi>Kent</hi> it muſt be in <hi>Kiffin,</hi> and not <hi>Nicholas Woodman</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his own glaſſe, pray neighbour look in your glaſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine; and further <hi>Luke</hi> mentions none that <hi>Wooodman</hi> Baptized, it is a queſtion therefore whether <hi>Woodman</hi> Baptized any or no. And laſtly, here are more then an 100 Baptiſts in and about <hi>Dover</hi> that were not Baptized by <hi>Woodman,</hi> nor by any that he Baptized, who are living witneſſes againſt the Quakers falſities, and can (if need require) give a better account of the Original and line of their Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:172652:7"/>then <hi>Luke Howard</hi> can: And thus you ſee the Quakers Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative of the Root and Riſe of the <hi>Baptiſts</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> is pluckt up Root and Rind: And to proceed to take notice of his fifth and ſixth page, where he ſaith, <hi>But ſome of thoſe baptized by</hi> William Kiffin <hi>changed their opinion, and believed the univerſal Love of God to all:</hi> Well; and what then, <hi>Why ſome,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>thought it their duty to be baptized into the univerſal Love of God; But,</hi> he ſaith, none were Baptized again in all <hi>Kent</hi> except one <hi>Cox</hi> of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Reply, Here is a great Cry and little wool, a talk of rebaptizing and yet but one in all <hi>Kent</hi> was Baptized; but then our hiſtorian tells us, the reſt held their Baptiſm but changed their opinion into the univerſal love of God, and devoutly preached it up; if they had been naturalized into that by their perticular baptiſm, and upon this the man falls to calumnizing ſtoutly, calling us a confuſed brood of Baptiſts all rooted in <hi>Babell</hi> and confuſion, blind leaders of the blind with other ſuch like terms, and he concludes that their baptiſm into the faith of particular election being falſe, neither branch nor fruit can be true. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply</hi> it is uſualy for ſuch as once owned and profeſſed the way of the Lord, and after depart from it as <hi>Luke Howard</hi> hath done, to become the fierceſt oppoſers of that truth they once profeſſed; ſee for example <hi>Acts</hi> 20, 29 and 30. and therefore 'tis no marvel if he give ſuch fowl meaſure to the Baptiſts; but to requite the <hi>Quaker</hi> for his kindneſs, that the Reader may ſee his Spirit is not good, <hi>I</hi> will ſhew where he would have found ſuch another brood of <hi>Baptiſts</hi> as he has found in <hi>Kent,</hi> namely, the Church at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the 3000, <hi>Acts</hi> the 2. <hi>were Baptized into the faith of Gods love to the Jews on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and after changed their opinion both Preachers and people, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leived the univerſal love of God to the Gentiles,</hi> alſo ſee Acts 11 18. <hi>when they heard theſe things, they held their peace, and gloryfied God ſaying, Then hath God granted to the Gentiles alſo Repentance un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to life,</hi> here they changed in their opinion but held their Baptiſm, for no mention is made of re-baptizing any of them.</p>
            <p>Now if this <hi>Quaker</hi> had lived amongſt them, and been led by the ſame ſpirit he now is, he might by the ſame rule he clamours a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us, have condemned them for a confuſed brood of Baptiſts, rooted in <hi>Babel</hi> and confuſion. Firſt Baptized into the particular
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:172652:7"/>and then changing their opinion into the General, and devoutly preach that up as <hi>Peter</hi> did, <hi>Acts,</hi> the 10. and thereby have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded them blind leaders of the blind, as he blindly accuſed us.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>I</hi> ſhall return to page the 8. where he tells us, that ſince <hi>Woodmans</hi> time there are many filthy unheard of abominations a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, both in ſpirit and practice, and there might be more ſaid, as ſome of our ſelves know, but that he tells his Reader he is not willing to relate in print except he be provoked to it, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Reply, Doth the man think, that <hi>I</hi> ſhould return him thanks for his civility in concealing that which he had not to ſay, or if ſaid, could not prove, but however he has diſcloſed his Maſter-piece, he ſhoots at random for he names no perſon amongſt us: and ſo hitts no perſon that <hi>I</hi> know of: for <hi>I</hi> know none amongſt the Baptiſts that are guilty of ſuch unheard of abominations as he talks of, and were not my neighbour <hi>Howard</hi> a <hi>Quaker,</hi> that pretends ſo much to plain dealing, <hi>I</hi> ſhould take this for very fowl dealing, to put forth in print ſuch a charge againſt a whole Congregation of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to reproach them, and mention no perſon or particular thing amongſt us, that the accuſed if guilty might be known, or if inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent might defend themſelves; but this being the meaſure the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker</hi> uſually meets to him that oppoſes him. <hi>I</hi> ſhall place this for ſome of his plain dealing.</p>
            <p>But to follow him a little further in his own Track, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n page 8 11 and 15 <hi>I</hi> find him very angry becauſe we bring forth a thing of ſo long a ſtanding, Calling us Wolves in Sheeps cloathing, and that the Ravening nature is ſtanding in us, which can look 9, or 10. years Back (ſaith he) to ſmite with the fiſt of wickedneſs, and to Perſecure an innocent people, and with many more ſuch evil terms he upbraids us, and here <hi>I</hi> may anſwer him with his own argument. Are the Baptiſts Ravenous, &amp;c. for look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing 10 years back, and is not <hi>Luke Howard</hi> by his own rule and Glaſſe, much more ravenous, who Ranges above twenty, yea, neare thirty years back, to rake up matter from his own Companion to reproach us with, and to ſmite us with the fiſt of falſhood; if <hi>Luke</hi> make another Glaſſe, <hi>I</hi> adviſe him to look in it and ſee himſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſend it out to others. And now <hi>I</hi> ſhall collect a few more of thoſe many accuſations, with which his book is ſtuffe, pag. the 10 he calls us blaſphemers againſt the light of Jeſus which they declare, calling it naturall, &amp; the Quakers dark light, with many more blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous words, as the Jews did of old, hereupon he brands us with
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:172652:8"/>odious terms of men-ſlayers and murderers, and that the body of death is ſtanding in us; where the murderer lives, and where the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents life is, whoſe wiſdom is earthly, ſenſual and Diveliſh, that bites at their heels, and accuſes us with things of many years ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and then as if he had forgot his own ſtory of 28 years ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he tells us page the 15. that if we had not been drunk with the Whores Cupp of abomination, and envious holyneſs, getting words to talk, and profeſſing in the ravenous nature, we would not fetch ſuch old matter againſt Quakers of ten years ſtanding and print it, &amp;c, To which upon the whole <hi>I</hi> anſwer, with that Scripture <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.3. <hi>Thinkeſt thou this, O man that Judgeſt them and doeſt the ſame things, that thou ſhalt eſcape the judgment, thine own mouth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns thee and not I, yea, thy wicked own lipps teſtifie againſt thee Job</hi> 15.6. for if the Baptiſts be ſuch wickeed perſons as <hi>Luke</hi> pretends, for reporting a truth of 10, years dat (which <hi>Luke</hi> in his conſcience knows it ſo) <hi>Is</hi> not <hi>Luke</hi> then by the ſame rule much worſe, in fetching up a far older ſtory, and that falls on two, as appears by his own glaſſe.</p>
            <p>Again, if <hi>Luke</hi> had proved by ſome convincing arguments, that the Quakers Light is Chriſt, and then made it appear that the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts had blaſphemed, in denying that men are redeemed and juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by that light within themſelves, and not rather by faith in the death, reſurrection and Aſſention of Chriſt without us, for us, which is the chief point in controverſie between us, and ſpared his bad language, this might have taken ſome impreſſion upon a judicious Reader. But it ſeems that <hi>Luke</hi> finds, that to Callumnize his op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſer is the eaſieſt way of anſwering, and 'tis like, himſelf is beſt furniſht with ſuch Arguments.</p>
            <p>Again, to ſhew the heat of his Anger againſt the Truth, and to render us vile and odious, he tells the World, That we make thoſe which we dip more foul in heart, and twofold more the Child of the Devil then they were before <hi>page</hi> 4. and 8. And then, as if he had given us a mortal wound, he exalts himſelf and his party as high as Heaven (in his own conceit) telling the world that they <hi>viz.</hi> the Quakers do worſhip God in ſpirit and truth, which the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil and all they that do his works of envie are out of, <hi>pag.</hi> 12. And then to ſhew himſelf to be no boaſting Phariſee, he tells me, That I do <hi>Caperna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m</hi>-like exalt my ſelf, and that for no other cauſe that I ſee, but my ſaying, that if the <hi>Quakers</hi> denied that they owned <hi>Charles Baily</hi> they would render themſelves falſe perſons.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:172652:8"/>
            <p>To all this I reply, that if <hi>Luke Howard</hi> were as able to prove, as he is apt to accuſe, he would be an able Quaker: But failing in his proofs, he appears more like a Scold then a ſober Chriſtian, whereas now if he had made it appear in ſome particular perſon or perſons, who after Baptiſm in water (according to the Command and Example of Chriſt, had becom twofold more the Childe or Children of Hell then before: He had made his Glaſs a great deal clearer to any Judicious Reader: But it may be he, ſuppoſing himſelf guided by an un-erring light, he counts his Say-ſo is proof ſufficient to condemn all his oppoſers.</p>
            <p>And then to beguiie his credulous Reader into a Fools Paradiſe, he tells him, <hi>The Quakers worſhip God in ſpirit and truth, which the devil and all that do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is works of Envie are out of.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> Theſe are great ſwelling words of vanity, but when <hi>Luke</hi> has proved the Quakers are ſo free from the Devil and his VVorks, and do worſhip God in ſpirit and truth (by comparing the Scriptures and their Practice together, it ſhall then be part of my Creed too, to believe they are ſuch, but not before.</p>
            <p>Now after all this with many more clamorous accuſations (as may be ſeen in his Looking-Glaſs againſt the Baptiſts, he concludes his fallacious Narrative with a boaſt, <hi>page</hi> 11. <hi>Our Rock is not like yours, our Enemies themſelves being Judges,</hi> ſaith he. And then <hi>(Oh ye fools) ſo ſoon as ye have liberty to meet, where you were afraid to meet before for fear of a man, and ye crept into cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> The Boaſter builds upon the Sand, and this his accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is as ſandy as his foundation: for <hi>I</hi> appeal to all the judicious inhabitants in <hi>Dover,</hi> who are VVitneſſes in this caſe, who know that whilſt the Quakers meet without any interruption, we were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted for ſeveral months together, almoſt every Lords day, at our publick Meeting-place, and there we continued till our Meeting-Houſe was defaced, the doors barrd and lockt up: After that, we met elſewhere in Town conſtantly; And truly, <hi>I</hi> cannot but admire, that the Quaker ſhould have the face to publiſh ſuch a falſhood in Print, in which the Magiſtrates and People of the Town, and his own Conſcience too (if not ſeared) will all bear witneſs againſt him, and on our part in this matter: but this is juſt like the reſt of his Glaſs.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
